Zhiwei Chang

Data/Research Scientist

Curious and persistent researcher with over 10 years of experience in theoretical and numerical (bio)physics ready to transfer to new role as Data Scientist. I love to enter new territories, acquire new knowledge and skills to solve the most challenging problems ahead. Being sceptic and imaginative both — with a can-do-it-all, grit and teamwork mentality — I am equipped to make unique contributions to the team.

SKILLS

Programming & Software

Python, Numpy, Pandas, Matplotlib, Seaborn, Jupyter Notebook, Scikitlearn, SQL, MATLAB/Octave, Mathematica, Git, Linux shell, Office, LaTeX

Technical

Regression (Linear, Multiple-Linear, Logistic, Polynomial, SVR, Random Forest), **Classification** (K-NN, SVM, Random Forest, Native Bayes), **Clustering** (K-means, Hierarchical), **Deep learning**, Project Management, Data Cleaning & Interpretation, Scientific writing & documentation

EXPERIENCE

2021.7 - CURRENT

To deep my understanding in machine learning and also benefit others, I began to rewrite Andrew Ng's course exercises Matlab code in Python. Moreover, I implement corresponding algorithms in Scikit-learn as a comparison and some problems are solved using different methods. I also explore and analyze the data sets in Kaggle. In addition, I solve algorithms and data structure problems in AlgoExpert. These projects can be found in my Github.

2018.5 - 2021.6

Massachusetts Institute of Technology

Postdoc Fellow/Independent Researcher

This position is mainly focused on measuring protein structures using solid-state nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR). During the COVID when MIT was closed, I developed a new physical theory to analyze/design the electromagnetic pulses used to manipulate protein nuclear spins. This independent work resulted two manuscripts which are now ready for submission. I also took the famous machine learning course by Andrew Ng on Coursera during this period.

2011.9 - 2017.7

Lund University

Ph. D Researcher

I switched to a more interdisciplinary area - biophysics, to do my PhD. Using protein and water proton as a probe, working closely with my supervisor, I derived quantum mechanical theories related to NMR and wrote corresponding simulation packages to study protein dynamics. This work resulted in 5 first-authorship papers in a well-known peer-reviewed journal.

2008.9 - 2011.7

Northwest Normal University

Master Student

As my thesis project, I was tasked with calculating the atomic structure of the "superheavy" element 117 and its lighter homologue Astatine. With very little supervision, I published 5 theoretical and simulation papers and some of my predictions have been cited and confirmed by CERN.



in

Dag Hammarskjölds väg 5H, 22464, Lund, SE

(+46) 765943720

zwchang@mit.edu
https://github.com/zwchang

www.linkedin.com/in/zhiwei-chang-015b2355

EDUCATION

2018.5 – 2021.7 **Postdoctoral Researcher**

Biophysical Chemistry

Massachusetts Institute of Technology, USA

2011.9 – **2017.7 Doctor of Philosophy**

Biophysical Chemistry Lund University, Sweden

2008.9 - 2011.7 **Master of Science**

Theoretical Physics

Northwest Normal University, China

2003.9 – 2007.7 Bachelor of Science

Theoretical Physics

Beijing Normal University, China

SCHOLARSHIPS & AWARDS

2018 3-year International Postdoc Grant (3.15 million SEK, Approval Rate: 15%)

Swedish Research Council (Vetenskapsrådet)

2013 Hakon Hanssons Travel Grant (15000 SEK)

Lund University

2011 Full Ph.D. Scholarship

Lund University

2010 "Outstanding Paper" Award

Northwest Normal University

LANGUAGES

MOTHER TONGUE Chinese

FLUENT English
ELEMENTARY Swedish

TEACHING

Two semesters as a teaching assistant tutoring Thermodynamics and Electromagnetism; three semesters as a lab instructor tutoring several Thermodynamics experiments.

PUBLICATIONS

Twelve manuscripts: two submitted, ten published (peer-reviewed), ten first-author, including *J. Chem. Phys.*, *J. Phys. Chem. A*, etc. Some key publications can be found in my Google scholar (zwchang@mit.edu).